MARCOS ORTIZ, PHD

970.312.6561 • Grand Junction, CO • marcos.ortiz.math@gmail.com • LinkedIn • gitHub

SUMMARY

I am a PhD Mathematician from the University of Iowa, with more than 14 years of academic and research experience. I excel at complex problem solving tasks, and I am seeking opportunities to apply these skills as a data scientist. My ideal workplace is one in which I am frequently challenged with new problems, and given opportunities drive product development forward. I enjoy exploring complex data, finding creative ways to gain actionable insights from it, and communicating those finding in ways that can be understood and utilized by teams and colleagues with a wide variety of backgrounds and expertise.

EXPERIENCE

Colorado Mesa University, Grand Junction, CO

2018 – present

Instructor of Mathematics

- Designed and implemented extensive inquiry based course materials for the Engineering Calculus sequence, as well as Linear Algebra, Differential Equations, and Discrete Mathematics.
- Adapted course material for remote learning in Precalculus, Calculus I, II, and III.
- Earned an overall score of 95% on student evaluations across all courses taught.
- Awarded the highest possible faculty performance rating, *Exceptional*, for the past 4 years in a row.

Grinnell College, Grinnell, IA

2015-2018

Visiting Assistant Professor

- Mentored advanced undergraduate summer research projects in topology and topological data analysis.
- Developed lectures, homework, exams, and student projects for Linear Algebra, Number Theory, Topology, and Abstract Algebra.

University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA

2009-2015

Graduate Fellow

- Conducted graduate research in topology, contact topology, and experimental mathematics
- Proved novel results in contact topology, establishing a classification of a mathematical phenomena under a broad set of hypotheses.
- Organized a graduate research group in topology, which drew speakers from a variety of fields, including contact topology, knot theory, and topological data analysis.

MACHINE LEARNING

Through coursework and certifications I have developed familiarity with many fundamental concepts and machine learning tools, including:

- Using popular machine learning libraries like NumPy, scikit-learn, Tensorflow, and keras
- Building and training supervised machine learning models for prediction and binary classification tasks, including linear regression and logistic regression
- Supervised learning (multiple linear regression, logistic regression, neural networks, and decision trees)
- Unsupervised learning (clustering, dimensionality reduction, recommender systems),
- Best practices for artificial intelligence and machine learning innovation (evaluating and tuning models, taking a data-centric approach to improving performance)

SKILLS AND CERTIFICATES

Mathematics: Research, Low Dimensional Topology, Experimental Mathematics, Topological Data Analysis, Linear Algebra, Abstract Algebra, Analysis, Number Theory, Differential Equations, Vector Calculus

Technical: python, C++, SQL, Excel, LATEX, git

Python Libraries: numpy, pandas, matplotlib, seaborn, tensorflow, keras, scikit-learn, scipy

Deeplearning.AI and Stanford University Certificates: •Machine Learning Specialization •Unsupervised Learning •Advanced Learning Algorithms •Supervised Machine Learning

EDUCATION

PhD, Mathematics University of Iowa Department of Mathematics	2015
Graduate Certificate in College Teaching University of Iowa Graduate College	2014
Masters, Mathematics University of Iowa Department of Mathematics	2012
B.Sc., Mathematics State University of New York at Buffalo Department of Mathematics	2009
B.A., Psychology University of North Carolina at Wilmington Department of Psychology	2004